<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

 <chapter xml:id="DataSources" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
      <title>Data Sources</title>
    </info>
    
    <section>
      <info>
        <title>Adding A New Data Source</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	Whilst we haven't yet had the time or resource to create a lovely graphical admin console for you system administrators we have tried to make it simple for you to add data sources to the Saiku platform.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Saiku server is shipped with Foodmart by default. So I shall show you how to import the steel-wheels schema and configure it to use a MySQL database connection.
      </para>
      <para>
	Firstly navigate to saiku-server/tomcat/webapps/saiku/WEB-INF/classes/saiku-datasources/ and copy the file named foodmart and rename it steelwheels. Next edit this new steelwheels file and configure it in a similar way to the following:
      </para>
      <para>
	<screen>
type=OLAP
name=steelwheels
driver=mondrian.olap4j.MondrianOlap4jDriver
location=jdbc:mondrian:Jdbc=jdbc:mysql://localhost/sampledata;Catalog=../webapps/saiku/steelwheels/steelwheels.mondrian.xml;JdbcDrivers=com.mysql.jdbc.Driver;
username=dbuser
password=password
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	So what we have done here is told Saiku the new name of the connection is steelwheels. We then told Saiku the location of the database and mondrian schema, for which I have created a steelwheels folder under the webapp/ directory. We finally set the database username and password. Once you have installed your schema definition, restart your server. It doesn't get much simpler than that.
      </para>
    </section>
      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Adding a new JDBC Driver</title>
	</info>
      <para>
	Obviously not everyone uses Hypersonic or MySQL to connect to their data warehouses. To use your specific database, please add the JDBC connector jar file to saiku-server/tomcat/webapps/saiku/WEB-INF/lib/ and then make the appropriate changes to the jdbc portion of the location string in the connection file.
      </para>
      </section>
 </chapter>